<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Obsidian]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/</link><image><url>https://gckanter.github.io/lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Obsidian</title><link>https://gckanter.github.io/</link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 06:56:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gckanter.github.io/lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 06:56:58 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></copyright><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator>Gareth Kanter</dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>Book Club: 'The Firm'</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Aug 03, 2024 10:54 PM<br><br>
<br>General reactions to the book
<br>How did the depiction of work/life balance (or lack thereof) affect you during the read?
<br>Did you come away with any reflections about your own relationship to work?
<br>What did you think about Grisham's portrayal of women? Ideally, Marisa and/or Katherine kicks this one off. This is also a time to share your favorite r/MenWritingWomen submissions.
<br><br>
<br>What do you think is successful or unsuccessful about Sydney Pollack's adaption?
<br>Is this a movie that stands alone from the book?
<br>How did you feel about some of these major changes:

<br>Abby and Mitch kept their old car in addition to the new car from The Firm. In the book, Abby also gets a new car.
<br>To some, Gene Hackman plays a decent amount older than how they imagine Avery Tolar. He also plays the role with much more melancholy than the character on the page.
<br>The reduction of Lamar &amp; Kay Quinn's prevalence in the story
<br>The girl on the beach constructs a "Knight in the Shining Armor" scenario for Mitch instead of just seducing him at the bar
<br>Abby honeypots Tolar in the Caymans instead of Tammy
<br>Mitch maintains his identity and life, but only by setting up every partner at the firm for prosecution and not providing any evidence against the Morolto family.
<br>Tammy and Ray getting together.


<br>Are there any changes other than the above that stuck out to you?
<br><br>I would like to open these categories to both the movie and the book if applicable. The full list of categories is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="TheRewatchablesCategories" data-href="TheRewatchablesCategories" href="https://gckanter.github.io/misc/therewatchablescategories.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">here</a>.<br>
<br>Most Rewatchable Scene
<br>The Neil McCauley “A Book about Metals” Award for Best Line from the Movie
<br>What's Aged the Best?
<br>What's Aged the Worst?
<br>Casting What Ifs
<br>The Vincent Chase Award: Are We Sure This Character Is Actually Good at Their Job?
<br>The "Ron Burgundy Flute" Award for the Best Time for a Pee Break
<br>The Steven A. Smith Hottest Take Award
<br>Just One Oscar
<br>Best Double Feature
<br>The "Andy and Red – Zihuatanejo" Award for What Happens the Next Day?
]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/clippings/bookclub_thefirm_discussion_2024_08_04.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Clippings/BookClub_TheFirm_Discussion_2024_08_04.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 06:03:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>"Elvis" Review</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Jan 09, 2023 4:39 PM<br><br>
<br>The accent –&nbsp;Butler's Elvis sounded like an alien from another planet whereas the actors playing the family around him sounded like they were from Memphis.
<br>The hair –&nbsp;the hair was perfectly quaffed and gelled throughout every scene. It bumped the most when he went to go visit Colonel Parker in the hospital after the Colonel's heart attack. It contributed to this effect of Butler seeming like an Elvis impersonator rather than Elivs. When you look back on archival footage, Elvis's hair is often messy and imperfect. Like a human being.
<br>Colonel Parker can write a contract on a napkin?
<br>No one knew Colonel Parker wasn't American? He has the strangest accent in the world and Elvis is SHOCKED to find out that he's not from West Virginia.
<br>Christmas Special
<br>Is it live?
<br>Are they filming over hours, days weeks?
<br>In what world can you meet with producers of an NBC show in the Hollywood sign, build TWO tv sets in order to fake out your own manager and a couple of ad sponsor execs?
<br>Elvis wanted to fuck his mom?
<br>When Elvis fired his manager –&nbsp;he could have done that the whole time?
<br>What happened with that hound dog on TV? They cut away and say that it was embarrassing, but I have no idea why.
<br><br>
<br>The King was well known for conducting all of his LA meetings in Dr. Evil’s secret lair behind the Hollywood sign.
<br>The movie depicts Elvis and BB King as personal friends. This is factual and excuses Elvis from any alleged cultural appropriation.
<br>As portrayed in Luhrmann’s film, Elvis did in fact want to fuck his mother
<br>Luhrmann cut around and enhanced music performances to make a two plus hour film from Presley’s limited catalog and numerous incomplete works.
<br>While the movie shows Elvis firing the Colonel on stage at the International, in reality, Elvis did do that, they just left out the part where he murmured to himself, “I guess I could have done that the whole time. Huh?”
<br>Austin Butler’s Elvis is shocked to learn that Colonel Parker isn’t from West Virginia. In real life, everyone was too embarrassed for Elvis to tell him that his manager with a sorta kinda Dutch accent was actually from the Netherlands. 
<br>The script, written by Baz Luhrmann &amp; Sam Bromwell and Baz Luhrmann, renders the King as a civil rights activist motivated by the assassinations of President Kennedy, Dr. King, and Bobby Kennedy. This depiction stretched the truth a little as Elvis was only recognized as a civil rights hero when he traveled back in time to stop slavery from ever happening.
<br>At one point in the Oscar nominated film, The Colonel drafts a legally binding contract on a cocktail napkin. The filmmakers took some artistic license in this scene as a cocktail napkin would only serve as a preliminary legal document. The terms could not be executed until they were tattooed on Elvis's lower abdomen. 
]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/essays/essay_2023_01_09_elvisreview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Essays/Essay_2023_01_09_ElvisReview.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 07:28:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA["<a data-href="Killers of the Flower Moon" href="misc/movies-&amp;-series/killers-of-the-flower-moon.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Killers of the Flower Moon</a>" Review]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Oct 24, 2023 9:08 AM<br><br>Some critics have praised Martin Scorsese and Eric Roth for their decision to shift the focus of this film away from Tom White (played by Jesse Plemmons) and toward the relationship between Mollie and Ernest Burkhart (played by Lily Gladstone and Leonardo DiCaprio respectively).<br>Scorsese himself discussed the move as resulting from a desire to avoid the pitfalls of the white savior trope. But the film and character at its center are much more perplexing. Scorsese latched onto Ernest Burkhart, who apparently takes up a much smaller chunk of the book than Tom White. If the goal of the film was to characterize DiCaprio's Ernest as a conflicted anti-hero, one torn asunder by true love for his wife and the temptations of greed, then it failed.<br>DiCaprio plays Ernest as a man who might be so stupid as to be totally ignorant of his Uncle W.K. Hale's (played by Robert De Niro) criminal empire. On the other hand, after a few years of matrimony with Mollie, and following the death of her cousin Millie, Ernest has seamlessly transitioned into recruiting local buffoons to doing "King" Hale's dirty work. There is not a moment spared in the film for Ernest to wonder if organizing the murder of his wife's family and friends might pose a problem for the woman he supposedly loves.<br>Scorsese seemed to intend to paint a picture of a man with a love corrupted by the ever-insidious forces of white supremacy. Even as John Lithgow's Prosecutor Peter Leaward forces Ernest, on the stand, to face the facts of the murders he's perpetrated against her family and friends and the fact that he poisoned her slowly for months, Ernest declares that he loves Mollie. He believes this despite his actions that stand in clear contrast to that idea. Racism has led him to this state of cognitive dissonance. That is perhaps the most interesting notion this film presents. But the irony is that while Scorsese intended to show respect and admiration for the Osage people in the process of making this film, that ever-insidious force led him to do just the opposite.<br>A man's greed and innate white supremacy turning him against the love of his life is an interesting story. A man's greed and innate white supremacy turning him into a sociopathic killer is an interesting story. Killers is caught betwixt and between. And to make matters worse, based on interviews, the filmmakers think that this movie is about Lily Gladstone's Mollie. <br>While Gladstone's performance hits every melancholic note with pitch perfect tone, she is not centered in this story. The structure of this film positions her as Ernest's victim-to-be, slowly, passively waiting for death to come to her from the place she dares not to expect. <br>Scorsese even ends the picture with her obituary. The final scene is a true crime radio broadcast summarizing the rest of the story. The part of a based-on-a-true-story film we’re used to seeing as white text over black. One can assume he means to use this format ironically, to show that this story should and must transcend pulp fascination. Instead, it only undermines his point. At the end of the day, Scorsese chose to show nearly every detail of the grotesque crimes perpetrated against the Osage people. And he chose to center it around a man he made out to be far more complex than he likely actually was. Scorsese himself appears on screen, stirred by the obituary he reads of Mollie Burkhart. But given everything that leads to this moment over 3 hours and 20 minutes, the tears in his eyes can’t help but read a little as the crocodile variety.<br>De Niro says "they won't remember," a meta commentary on the way this story will be forgotten in U.S. history. But further into his justification for Ernest taking the fall, he gets at this idea that people don't really care. It's the cementing of a problematic idea at the heart of this film that people know what kills them, but they don't do anything about it. The Osage as depicted in this film know that "the white man's food" will give them diabetes, but they eat it anyways. They know that white men keep marrying their daughters and their daughters keep dying but they do it anyway. They know that King Hale cashes life insurance policies on them and cashes out, yet they trust him anyways. They see the wolves, standing center frame in the picture, but they do nothing. The film wanted to show the horrific blatant nature of these crimes, but in doing so, unfairly depicted the Osage as willfully and woefully ignorant people.<br><br>
<br>Can you see the wolves in this picture all the way to people don’t really care
<br>Ernest is caught between being naive, sociopathic, capable of a cognitive dissonance heretofore unseen

<br>it might have been an interesting character, but it feels like Scorsese going out of his way to humanize a man from history who Occam’s razor dictates simply saw Mollie Burkhardt and her family as subhuman and treated them worse than that 
<br>“It’s just to slow her down” he tells himself 


<br>Scorsese ends the picture with true crime radio broadcast summarizing the rest of the story. The part of a based on a true story film we’re used to seeing in white text over black. One can assume he means to use this format ironically, to show that this story should and must transcend pulp fascination. Instead, it only undermines his point. At the end of the day, Scorsese chose to show nearly every detail of the grotesque crimes perpetrated against the Osage people. And he chose to center it around a man he made out to be far more complex than he actually was. Scorsese himself appears on screen, stirred by the obituary he reads of Mollie Burkhardt. But given everything that leads to this moment over 3 hours and 20 minutes, the tears in his eyes can’t help but read A little as the croxodile variety. 
<br>Scorsese seemed to intend to paint a picture of a man with a love corrupted by the ever-insidious forces of white supremacy. Even forced to face facts of the murders he's perpetrated against her family and friends and the fact that he poisoned her slowly for months, Ernest declares that he loves Mollie. He believes this despite his actions that stand in clear contrast to that idea. The irony is that Scorsese intended to show respect and admiration for the Osage people in the process of making this film, but that ever-insidious force led him to do just the opposite all the while believing he was making the right choice.
]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/essays/essay_2023_10_24_killersoftheflowermoonreview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Essays/Essay_2023_10_24_KillersOfTheFlowerMoonReview.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 19:13:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>"A Nightmare on Elm Street" Review</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Oct 30, 2023 8:26 PM<br>Am I reading too much into this movie?<br>After watching A Nightmare on Elm Street last night, I did not like the ending. But after thinking over it, I'm wondering if the movie has something much more profound going on. If Reagan-era America can be criticized for falsely propping up the economy with junk bonds and creating this hyper-commercialized culture, then maybe the movie is about the generation of teens in the 1980s who have been handed a raw deal by their parents' generation. It's a movie both literally about death from dreams and figuratively about the death of the American dream.<br>It's implied that the parents of the four children targeted in the film were among those who formed the mob that hunted down and killed Krueger, who by the way, was let off by a failure in the legal system. Now, years later, Krueger has come to reap what those parents have sowed. Krueger's origin story is a reflection of the anxieties that the short term gains of electing Reagan and the rapid economic growth that came with it will lead to a much much greater pitfall, screwing over the next generation.<br>The movie also pointedly contains no depiction of a "functional" family. Tina's mother's concern for her daughter's nightmare that opens the film is interrupted by a menacing looking boyfriend who wants her to return to bed. Tina's mother also sports some welts on her face, presumably from this man. After Tina's death, the cops say they try to reach her, but we never see the mother return from Vegas and grieve her daughter's death. In fact, the only funeral we do see is for Rod. It's attended by his friends and their parents, but there is no indication that Rod even has a family. Nancy's parents meanwhile are split up. Her father is too absorbed in his work to heed Nancy's warnings about Krueger, even using his daughter as bait to catch Rod. Her mother is too absorbed with the other end of a wine bottle (portrayed with a borderline hilarious level of cliché) to do the same. Glen's parents purport to be the most typical caregivers in the film, but their overly protective instincts lead directly to his death.<br>Now, back to the ending. Nancy seemingly defeats Krueger in the real world by turning her back on him and refusing to give him power (through her fear of him). It's a surprisingly earnest and logical solution to a villain who seems to embody chaos and absurdity. Of course, that solution is immediately yanked back with the subsequent scene which in hindsight, reads as the most terrifying one in the movie. Nancy's mom sees off her daughter as she joins the rest of her friends in a sweet new convertible. Everyone is manic and comments on a morning fog that will surely burn off soon. The convertible's roof triggers on its own and it is patterned with Krueger's signature sweater stripes. The kids scream and cry for help from Nancy's mother who smiles and waves vacantly just before Krueger's claws reach out through the front door and pull her inside.<br>The movie seems to be saying fears exist for a reason. You cannot just turn your back on them, for if you do, you will have only accomplished making yourself ignorant to your fate. It's a bleak message, but then again so were the 1980s if you took the time to look just below the surface.<br>
Beyond a pointy-headed analysis of the deeper meaning of the film (which may not even be there), I also want to shout out the movie's juxtaposition of absurdist dream-logic horror and nauseating real-world consequences, which was deeply unsettling. Somehow seeing Tina torn apart on the ceiling of her room or Glen rendered into human mulch is even scarier having been preceded by Krueger waving his six foot arms or licking Nancy through the phone. It's said over and over that comedy and horror are two halves of the same coin. Structurally, both rely on setting up tension and the releasing that tension. Elm Street effectively employs both to amplify its desired result.
]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/essays/essay_2023_10_30_anightmareonelmstreetreview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Essays/Essay_2023_10_30_ANightmareOnElmStreetReview.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 19:13:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>"Paddington" Review</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Dec 06, 2023 3:42 PM<br>The most charming thing about this movie is its ability to tell a story through a child's lens without actually tying the point of view to a character. And it does this without drifting into something puerile at every opportunity where a lesser movie would have.<br>A moment in the film that exemplifies this high-wire act is when Nicole Kidman's Millicent takes a dock worker to her secret taxidermy lab in an adjoining room. The busts of animal heads in the first room are connected to their full bodies in the adjoining room. Funny to an adult viewer and simply logical to the younger audience.<br>Also, the license plate Millicent goes to great lengths to track down for Matt Lucas's taxi driver Joe is CAB BIE. I mean come on.]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/essays/essay_2023_12_06_paddingtonreview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Essays/Essay_2023_12_06_PaddingtonReview.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 04:33:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>"Alien: Resurrection" Review</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Feb 17, 2024 7:32 PM<br>Alien: Resurrection is of course nothing compared to the works of sublimity that are Alien and Aliens. But to borrow a sub-genre from The Big Picture podcast, it is one of the better "junk sci-fi" movies I've seen in a long time.<br>The below-the-line crew on this movie are executing at a high level -- worthy of the predecessor movies in the franchise. The production design, score, costumes, sound design, and creature effects are all immensely affecting.<br>The movie also takes stabs at big ideas. Ideas of creationism, motherhood, and evolution. Nothing mind-shattteringly different than the previous films, but it does go for it and pushes those themes further than they have been pushed before. While it lacks subtlety and -- as one Redditor mentioned in a comment read aloud before the movie started -- class.<br>And this is where things get really interesting. This fourth Alien movie has the building blocks of something great, but then the director, Jean-Pierre Jeunet, and/or the writer, one Joss Whedon, take big swings. Sure, the movie might be tonally inconsistent, the very premise of the film might be lacking any sort of sci-fi logic to it, but the gains are so so so worth it. The result is a deeply bizarre movie with a couple of authentically depraved sequences that made me hoot and holler from the couch. Nothing seems out-of-bounds for this film. I wouldn't fault someone for being offended by its vulgar and on-the-nose handling of some topics, but it sure entertained me.<br>And here we enter spoilers for the rest of the review.<br>The above alludes of course to the three banner sequences of the film:<br>
<br>'Number 8' meets 'Numbers 1-7'
<br>The birth of the Newborn
<br>The death of the Newborn
<br>Watching Ripley kill her fellow failed Cronenbergien clones was genuinely an emotional sequence in huge part due to Weaver's extraordinary ability to continue to sell this grim universe to us nearly 20 years after she first played the role.<br>Now onto my favorite part of this movie. The Newborn. Before this movie started, I was discussing with my friends the upcoming Alien: Romulus and what we even wanted from an Alien prequel/sequel at this point. Answers were hard to come by. Watching the Newborn rise from the womb of the hybrid Alien Queen, I finally knew. This. This is what I had been wanting. I want to see the Xenomorphs continue to evolve in their nightmarish way.<br>This is the movie's stroke of genius. The hybrid Alien Queen has gained the ability to reproduce directly, like a human. It's presented as a chilling next step for the Xenomorph race. A critical adaptation in their incessant quest to become the greatest most perfect killing machines in the universe. But now that the Newborn is slightly human it loses the edge that all Xenomorphs have -- ruthlessness. The Newborn's first act is to murder its birth mother and then go to Ripley for comfort. It rejects its alien heritage, preferring the more human side of the genetic hybrid coin. The Newborn, like Winona Ryder's Call, wants to ignore the unholy nature of its creation. But while Call and hybrid-Ripley have a future in the ruins of human society, the Newborn is too far gone. It is a monster, just like with hybrid-Ripley 'Number 7,' Ripley decides the only fate it deserves is death.<br>Is Ripley right? I don't know. Where previous Alien movies deal with a simple binary -- human versus monster -- Alien: Resurrection lays out a spectrum where the line between the two binaries is much murkier. And in the spirit of the whole franchise, the pure humans are are more cruel and murderous than the Xenomorphs at the opposite end. In that way, this movie is a fitting conclusion to the Ripley Alien films.]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/essays/essay_2024_02_17_alienresurrectionreview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Essays/Essay_2024_02_17_AlienResurrectionReview.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 04:33:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<span class="dataview dataview-inline-query"><span>The Rewatchables Categories</span></span>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Jul 29, 2024 7:56 AM<br><br>
<br>Most Rewatchable Scene
<br>The Neil McCauley “A Book about Metals” Award for Best Line from the Movie (updated)
<br>What's Aged the Best?
<br>What's Aged the Worst?
<br>The Dion Waiters Award for Best Heat Check Performance
<br>The Joey Pants "That Guy" Award
<br>The "Ruffalo/Hanna/Rubinek/Partridge" Overacting Award
<br>Casting What Ifs
<br>Half-Assed Internet Research
<br>Probably Unanswerable Questions
<br>Sequel, Prequel, Limited Series, or All Black Remake (updated)
<br>Apex Mountain
<br>Who Won the Movie?
<br>Picking Nits
<br>Recasting Couch (retired sort of since the answer's always Sydney Sweeney)
<br>Is this Movie Better with Danny Trejo, Steve Buscemi, or Michael K. Williams? (update below)
<br><br>
<br>The "Den of Thieves Benihana" Award for Scene Stealing Location
<br>The "Great Shot Gordo" Award for Most Cinematic Shot
<br>The Vincent Chase Award: Are We Sure This Character Is Actually Good at Their Job?
<br>The "Big Kahuna Burger" Award for Best Use of Food and Drink
<br>The "Butch's Girlfriend" Award for the Weakest Link in the Film
<br>The "Ron Burgundy Flute" Award for the Best Time for a Pee Break
<br>Is There a Better Title for this Movie?
<br>The Steven A. Smith Hottest Take Award
<br>The Teddy KGB Award for the Actor in a Completely Different Movie
<br>Hall of Fame Plaque
<br>Just One Oscar
<br>Best Double Feature
<br>Best Race Horse Name from this Movie
<br>What Piece of Memorabilia Would You Want From This Movie?
<br>The "Andy and Red – Zihuatanejo" Award for What Happens the Next Day?
<br>The Coach Finstock Award for Best Life Lesson
<br>The “Slow Ride” / "Kid Cudi – Pursuit of Happiness" Award for Best Needle Drop
<br>Is this movie better with Wayne Jenkins, Danny Trejo, Sam Jackson, J.T. Walsh, Byron Mayo, Harling Mays, Evil-Laughing Ramon Raymond, or Philip Baker Hall?
]]></description><link>https://gckanter.github.io/misc/therewatchablescategories.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Misc/TheRewatchablesCategories.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Gareth Kanter]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 15:00:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>